A Guide to the Manuscripts of James Branch Cabell, 1919-1948, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Manuscripts of James Branch Cabell, 1919-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5618-d
This collection consists of 53 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the library on 1959 February 26.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains manuscripts, photographs and prints and miscellaneous papers such as pamphlets and proofs of James Branch Cabell.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - First draft of Smirt[1934], TMs,AMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 125 p. (Box 8)
  - Second version of Smirt[1934], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 182 p. (Box 9)
  - First draft of Smith[1935], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 230 p. (Box 9)
  - Second draft of Smith[1935], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 110 p. (Box 9)
  - "Some Objections to Branch Cabell" n.d., TMsS. [w/auto. corrections.] 3 p. (Box 9)
  - First draft of Some of Us[1930], TMs. [w/clippings tipped in; w/auto. corrections and additions.] 77 p. (Box 9)
  - First draft of Something About Eve[1927], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 75 p. (Box 9)
  - Discarded pages from Something About Eve[1927], TMs, AMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 200 p. (Box 9)
  - Second draft of Something about Eve, 2 v. [1927], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 170 p. (Box 9)
  - "Sonnets from Antan" n.d., AMsS. 10 p. (Box 10)
  - First drafts of Special Delivery [1933], TMs, AMs. [w/auto. corrections.] ca. 130 p. (Box 10)
  - First version of Straws and Prayer Books, 2 v. [1924], TMs (Box 10)
    [w/auto. corrections & note.] ca. 230 p.
  - First version of Taboo1920 Dec., TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 19 p. (Box 10)
  - There Were Two Pirates [1946], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 72 p. (Box 10)
  - First drafts of These Restless Heads[1932], TMsS, TMs. [w/ auto. corrections.] (carbon) and AMs. ca. 300 p. (Box 10)
  - Printer's copy of These Restless Heads1931 Jul, TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 150 p. (Box 11)
  - "The Thin Queen of Elfhame" n.d., TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 7 p. (Box 11)
  - "Townsend of Lichfield" [1929], TMsS, AMs.[w/auto. corrections on TMsS.]12 p. (Box 11)
  - Unrevised carbon of "Townsend of Lichfield" [1929], TMs(carbon). 10 p. (Box 11)
  - Printer's copy of "Townsend of Lichfield" 1929 Apr 14, TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 24 p. (Box 11)
  - "Turtle-Meat and Broomsticks," review of From a Southern Porch by Dorothy Scarborough 1919 Nov., TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 4 p. (Box 11)
  - Clean copy of "Turtle-Meat and Broomsticks" 1919 Nov., TMs. 4 p. (Box 11)
  - First version of "The Water of Airdra" [1935], TMs. 10 p. (Box 11)
    [became "Book of Elair" in; w/auto. corrections.]
  - Second version of "The Water of Airdra" [1935], TMs. 13 p. (Box 11)
  - Draft of "The Way of Ecben" [1929], AMs. 3 p. (Box 11)
  - First draft of Part I of "The Way of Ecben" [1929], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 22 p. (Box 11)
  - Later version of "The Way of Ecben" [1929], TMs. [w/auto. corrections and additions.] 69 p. (Box 11)
  - First version of "The Ways of Women" n.d., Photostat of TMs. 7 p. (Box 11)
  - First version of first part of "The White Robe" [1928], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 8 p. (Box 11)
  - First draft of "The White Robe" [1928], TMs. [Inscribed to Frances Newman; w/auto. corrections.] 32 p. (Box 11)
  - Printer's copy of "The White Robe" [1928], TMs. 32 p. (Box 11)
  - "The Witch-Woman" [1948], TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 8 p. (Box 11)
  - "A Word to My Followers" n.d., TMs. [w/auto. corrections.] 4 p. (Box 11)
- Photographs and Prints
  - Cabell Room, Valentine Museum, Richmond, Virginia n.d., Picture postcard (Box 11)
  - Exhibit of Cabell material atu [University of Florida] n.d., Photo (Box 11)
  - 43 illustrations by Frank C. Pap頦or books by James Branch Cabell n.d., Engravings (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes and parts of essays, 13 unidentified pages n.d., AMs,TMs (Box 11)
  - "Bibliographic Check List of the Works of James Branch Cabell" by Merle Johnson 1921, Pamphlet. [signed by author.] 28 p. (Box 11)
  - Two copies of "James Branch Cabell" by H.L. Mencken 1928, Pamphlet. 33 p. (Box 11)
  - "Joseph Hergesheimer, an Essay in Interpretation" by James Branch Cabell 1921, Pamphlet. 27 p. (Box 11)
  - 2 copies of "The Nightmare Has Triplets, An Author's Notes on Smire" by J.B.C. 1937, Pamphlet. 14 p. (Box 11)
  - "Of Ellen Glasgow, an Inscribed Portrait" by J.B.C. and Ellen Glasgow 1938, Pamphlet. 16 p. (Box 11)
  - The First Gentleman of America [1942], Corrected galley proofs. 71 strips. (Box 11)
  - Hamlet Had an Uncle [1940], 70 strips. Corrected galley proofs. (Box 11)
  - "The Jewel Merchants" [1921], Corrected page proofs. 63 pp. (Box 11)
  - Jurgen. Penguin Edition n.d., Page proofs. 71 strips. (Box 12)
  - "A Little More About Eve" [1928], Corrected galley proofs. 4 strips. (Box 12)
  - "A Note for the Intending Reader" [1927], Corrected page proofs. 3 p. (Box 12)
  - Quiet, Please [1952], Corrected page proofs. 105 p. (Box 12)
  - 2 groups of The St. Johns[1943], Corrected galley proofs. 78 strips each (Box 12)
  - The St. Johns [1943], Corrected page proofs. 317 p. (Box 12)
  - The St. Johns [1943], Corrected page proofs. [Large paged proof sheets.] p. 1-318 (Box 12)
  - Illustrations of opening sections of The Silver Stallion[1925], Galley proofs. 5 strips. (Box 12)